<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A declaration and order of his Excellency the Lord Generall Cromwell, and his Councill of Officers: for the continuance of the assesment for six moneths, from the 24th. of June 1653. to the 25th. of December following; at the rate of one hundered and twenty thousand pounds by the moneth, towards the maintenance of the armies and navies of this Common wealth. June 9. 1653. Ordered by his Excellency the Lord Generall Cromwell with the advice of his Councill of Officers, that this declaration be forthwith printed and published. William Malyn Secret.</title>
            <author>Cromwell, Oliver, 1599-1658.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1653</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 9 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 4 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A80885</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C7055</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1062_2</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R209604</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99868472</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99868472</idno>
            <idno type="VID">169140</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A80885)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 169140)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 158:E1062[2])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A declaration and order of his Excellency the Lord Generall Cromwell, and his Councill of Officers: for the continuance of the assesment for six moneths, from the 24th. of June 1653. to the 25th. of December following; at the rate of one hundered and twenty thousand pounds by the moneth, towards the maintenance of the armies and navies of this Common wealth. June 9. 1653. Ordered by his Excellency the Lord Generall Cromwell with the advice of his Councill of Officers, that this declaration be forthwith printed and published. William Malyn Secret.</title>
                  <author>Cromwell, Oliver, 1599-1658.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 5, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by and for H. Hills, G. Calvert and T. Brewster, and are to be sold at the Black Spread-Eagle, and at the Three Bibles near the West end of Pauls,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1653.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>England and Wales. --  Army --  Appropriations and expenditures --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Taxation --  England --  Law and legislation --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:169140:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A DECLARATION AND ORDER Of his EXCELLENCY the LORD GENERALL Cromwell, AND HIS COUNCILL OF OFFICERS: For the continuance of the Aſſeſment for ſix moneths, from the 24<hi rend="sup">th.</hi> of <hi>June</hi> 1653. to the 25<hi rend="sup">th.</hi> of <hi>December</hi> following; at the rate of one hundered and twenty thouſand pounds by the moneth, towards the maintenance of the Armies and Navies of this Common wealth.</p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>seal of the Commonwealth</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <floatingText type="license" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <opener>
                     <dateline>
                        <date>June 9. 1653.</date>
                     </dateline>
                  </opener>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Ordered by his Excellency the Lord Generall</hi> CROMWELL <hi>with the advice of his Councill of Officers, That this Declaration be forthwith printed and publiſhed.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>WILLIAM MALYN Secret.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON.</hi> Printed by and for <hi>H. Hills, G. Calvert</hi> and <hi>T. Brewſter,</hi> and are to be ſold at the <hi>Black Spread-Eagle,</hi> and at the Three <hi>Bibles</hi> near the Weſt end of <hi>Pauls,</hi> 1653.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:169140:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:169140:2"/>
            <head>A DECLARATION AND ORDER Of his EXCELLENCY the LORD GENERALL CROMVVEL, AND HIS COUNCEL of OFFICERS: For the continuance of the Aſſeſment to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the maintainance of the Armies and Navies of this Common-wealth for ſix moneths, from the 24<hi rend="sup">th.</hi> of <hi>June</hi> 1653. to the 25<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. of <hi>December</hi> following; at the rate of one hundred and twenty thouſand pounds by the moneth</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Lthough we are very ſenſible of the great and heavy Taxes, &amp; other publique bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens, which for the preſent are lying upon this Nation, and that nothing is to be more wiſhed &amp; endeavoured, next after the glory of God, and ſecuring of this great Cauſe, than
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:169140:3"/> the eaſe of the People in this particular: Yet conſidering the great and important occaſions and engagements of this Common-wealth at this time, both at Land and at Sea, requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring greater ſummes of money, than can be an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered out of other publique receipts, which through the former improvident management of affaires, are either exhauſted, or clogged with vaſte anticipations; and that without a ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply of money by continuing of the monethly Aſſeſment for ſome time longer, the Armies in <hi>England, Scotland</hi> &amp; <hi>Ireland,</hi> would be neceſſitated to burthen the People with free quarter, the Warre with the united Provinces of the Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therlands, of ſo much concernment to the wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faire of this Nation, be put in danger of miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carrying; and the other affaires of this Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth, fall into diſorder and confuſion.</p>
            <p>And becauſe the Perſons to whom the Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pream Authority, according to our former De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration is to be committed, cannot aſſemble time enough to take care therein, the Act of Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſment expiring the <hi>24.</hi> of this preſent <hi>June.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In this exegency, and upon this extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary occaſion, it is thought neceſſary to De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare and Order, and it is hereby Declared and Ordered by the Lord Generall, with the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of his Councill of Officers; That the laſt Act of Aſſeſment beginning the <hi>25</hi> of <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cember,</hi> and ending the <hi>24</hi> of <hi>Iune:</hi> whereby one hundred &amp; twenty thouſand pounds by the moneth is laid upon the ſeverall Counties, Cit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, Townes, and places therein mentioned, and every Clauſe therein contained, the ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Taxes and Payments therein expreſſed,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:169140:3"/> and the Powers and Authorities thereby given to all and every the Commiſſioners, Commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tees, or Perſons, or any of them named or men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned in the ſaid Act, ſhall endure and have continuance for ſix moneths longer, from the ſaid four and twentieth day of <hi>Iune 1653,</hi> unto the five and twentieth of <hi>DECEMBER</hi> next following, to all intents and purpoſes, as if the ſaid Act had been at firſt made to have continuance for twelve moneths from the ſaid five and twentieth day of <hi>December 1652.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And all perſons impoured by, or by vertue of the ſaid Act as Commiſſioners or otherwiſe, are hereby required and enjoyned, to rate, aſſeſſe, levy and collect the ſaid ſix moneths Aſſeſment, and to execute and do all matters whatſoever relating thereto as fully and amply to all intents and purpoſes, as they are enabled by the ſaid Act, to levy and Collect the laſt ſix moneths Aſſeſment.</p>
            <p>And further, that the ſaid Commiſſioners for the ſeveral and reſpective Counties, Cities and Towns, do meet at the moſt common and uſuall place of meeting in each of the ſaid Counties, Cities and Towns, for which they are Commiſſioners, reſpectively on or before the four and twentyeth day of this in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant <hi>Iune;</hi> and the ſaid Commiſſioners, or ſo many of them as ſhall then and there attend, and be preſent, ſhall cauſe this declaration to be put in execution, and ſhall thereupon ſend out their Warrants for the Aſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, collecting, and paying, the ſaid ſix mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neths Tax, ſo as the firſt three of the ſaid ſix moneths Aſſeſment, be paid into the Receivers Generall, upon or before the <hi>30</hi> day of <hi>Iuly</hi> next enſuing, and the laſt three moneths be paid, as aforeſaid, upon or before the firſt day of <hi>November</hi> following.</p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:169140:4"/>
            <p>And for that it is intended that an exact ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count ſhall be given of all moneys which ſhall be Aſſeſſed, Leavied, &amp; Collected throughout this Nation by vertue hereof, It is hereby required, That the ſeveral Receivers Generall of this Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſment in the reſpective Counties and places, do within fourteene dayes after the end of the ſaid ſix moneths, returne a perfect account of all the moneys they ſhall receive thereupon, to the Committee for the Army.</p>
            <p>And ſeeing the ſaid Aſſeſment is continued upon no other grounds then are before expreſſed, It is not doubted, but the good and well-af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected people of this Nation, who ſtill retaine ſound and honeſt Principles, will chearfully act in their ſeverall places and ſtations, to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote and further this ſervice.</p>
            <p>And if any, upon what pretence ſoever, ſhall refuſe to pay the ſaid Aſſeſments or diſcourage or weaken the hands of others therein: All<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though we doubt not, but all their endeavours in this kind will prove ineffectuall, yet they are to be looked upon, and proceeded againſt as thoſe who from a Spirit of Malignity and oppoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to the Cauſe of God in this Land (though upon other pretences) have indeavoured, as far as in them lies, to ſubiect the People of <hi>England, Ireland,</hi> and <hi>Scotland,</hi> to free quarter, and to bring the Navy into diſcontent for want of pay at this time, when this Nation is engaged in ſo great a Warre at Sea: hoping thereby to plunge theſe Nations againe into troubles, and give new advantages to the Common Enemy.</p>
            <p>And in caſe any of thoſe who have formerly been Inſtrumental and Helpers in this great Cauſe, ſhall be found in their number, although it will be
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:169140:4"/> matter of great trouble &amp; grief to us to ſee men thus by degrees fall ſhort, divide, and withdraw themſelves from publique ends; Yet as the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtacy, &amp; turning away of many amongſt us for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly, who at firſt ſeemd to be zealous promoters of this work, hath not been able to keep it at a ſtand, ſo our truſt and confidence is, that now through the grace and goodneſſe of God; nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the neutrality and indifferency of ſome, nor the defection and oppoſition of others, no, though ſo groſſe and open, as to cloſe with the Enemies of the power and life of godlineſſe, ſhall be any hinderance or prejudice thereunto: But that the ſame Spirit and preſence which hath hitherto helped us in our greateſt difficul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and moſt eminent dangers; will ſtill owne us and the reſt of his People in this Land, and enable us to perſevere unto the end againſt all diſcouragements whatſoever.</p>
            <p>And it is hereby further declared, That all and every the Commiſſioners, Committees, and other perſons whatſoever which ſhall act, do or execute any thing by vertue of, and in pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuance of this Declaration and Order, ſhall be ſaved harmleſſe and indemnified.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Signed by the appointment of his Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency the Lord Generall, with the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of his Councill of Officers. <hi>Will. Malyn.</hi>
                  </hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="approbation">
            <p>
               <hi>I</hi> Doe hereby appoint, that the Declaration of the Army, for the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance of the Aſſeſsment for ſix moneths, be printed by and for <hi>Henry Hills, Giles Calvert,</hi> and <hi>Thomas Brewſter,</hi> and that no other Printer doe preſume to print the ſame, or any part thereof, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out my ſpeciall Order, as they will anſwer the contrary. Given under my hand the <hi>9<hi rend="sup">th</hi>
               </hi> of <hi>June, 1653.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>O. CROMWELL.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
